Welcome back.
Let's talk about inheritance.
A core aspect of object oriented programming is inheritance which means passing knowledge down.
Remember at the start of this journey we decided that we want to create this game.
This fairy tale game that had all these characters and we started with else just a couple of elves but
as you can see our goal is to have many things we want to have maybe a dragon a knight a king and queen
maybe some magicians.
Yes even Dracula.
So using this object oriented programming principle of inheritance how could we accomplish this with
the work that we've already done.
Let's have a look.
We have our elf class here.
Yes we've seen it before and it shouldn't be anything new.
But let's say that I wanted to have a new player and this player is actually an ogre called Shrek.
How would I go about creating the soldier.
The one thing I could do is to copy and paste this code and create an ogre class.
I mean that's copying pasting dry code that eventually we want to avoid because as we keep copying and
pasting copying and pasting we just have repeated code which gets messy.
So one option that we might have here is well let's just copy the elf and maybe you can extend it.
So for example if I want to copy Fiona let's say Fiona over here if I click Run I have this health class
or elf instance with all these properties now in order to copy while you already have.
We can just do something like this.
We can say const Polgar and Bulger is going to equal.
Well let's clone Fiona and as I've shown you before we can do dot dot dot spread operator and then just
do Fiona if I do this.
Let's remove the spaces and I look at what ogre is now and I click Run look at that.
I've copied Fiona into the ogre variable and the interesting thing here is if I do ogre dot underscore
underscore proto underscore underscore what do I get.
I get an empty object.
What if I do Fiona
I have elf so I've cloned the object but ogre no longer has ELF as the class the base class so that
if I do hear console dialogue Fiona equals ogre clone and I click Run Oh and I don't the clone here
it should just be ogre I get false these objects are not referencing the same place in memory they're
completely different things but I've also lost this chain this prototype all inheritance chain I can't
even do ogre dot attack
No I don't have attack so that's a problem how can we extend this this work that we've currently had
and this is where inheritance comes in and you used to be really difficult to do with JavaScript before
we had this class syntax it involved a lot of ugly prototype code that luckily for us is now a lot cleaner
so let's have a look to start off to make naming a lot better I'm going to change the class here to
character because all characters in this game are going to have name and a weapon and they can attack.
That's great.
And now from this character I'm going to create a class elf that extends which is a keyword this character
class this is something called Sub classing an object oriented programming that is we have a base class
or a super class and a subclass that is we want to inherit from the character class all these properties
and methods and create something new out of it extend it with health let's have a look if I just do
this and I click Run.
All right I get undefined.
Let's see what Fiona is right now.
If I do Fiona and click Run.
All right look at that.
Everything is still working.
I have elf name Fiona weapons ninja All right great.
But you know what.
Let's make this a little bit more interesting.
Let's say that the elf characters in this game they also have an extra property that they can have.
Maybe it's a type property as to what type of ELF they are.
So let's build that out.
How do we go about doing that.
Well in here let's add the type of property.
If I do a construct right here and I do this dot name or this dot type equals type and let's say that
we receive a type parameter in here.
How is this going to work.
We have to instantiate the elf class and we give it the name and the weapon.
But we also want to have the type.
So maybe we'll do this we'll say name and weapon.
And the third parameter will be type.
So all say that type of the self.
I'm going to change the name from Fiona to Dobie.
The name is going to be Dobie and the attack is going to be well or the weapon is just going to be a
cloth and the type of Elf It's going to be a house elf All right.
If I do this let's see what happens.
I'm going to click Run reference here must call super constructor and derive class before accessing
this or returning from derived constructor.
Does that make sense.
Not really right.
I mean that's a pretty confusing error message.
What is it saying in order for us to have our constructor and be able to use this and know what this
is referring to which is Elf and not the character because remember we have both name and weapon.
We have this special keyword called super for superclass and this superclass we call like this and by
doing inside of the constructor the super call it says Hey call the superclass what's the superclass
of elf.
Well that's character.
It extends character so it goes up and calls the constructor so that we create this on name and this
dot map.
So in here we have to pass it name and weapon.
Now I know this is a little bit confusing.
This whole super thing is just a standard especially with classic class based languages where super
is referring to the superclass let's have a look here.
If I click Run look at that I got elf that is Dobie weapon is a cloth and has a type.
Well it's a household.
And if I use Dolby dot attack
attack with cloth.
Now very effective but it's working.
Now let's go over this one more time.
When we do class elf extends character it means hey extend and set the prototype.
That is the underscore underscore Prado to point to character.
So elf now has a prototype chain optic character.
It's saying Hey anytime you run an instance of elf like Dobie and a uses a property or a method that
I don't have.
Well then look up to character and tell me if character has the constructor is our own constructor just
for the elf class.
This is something that only gets run with an elf not with a character.
And in here we can leave it as is but if we want to set any sort of property that is use the this keyword
we have to call super and say Hey call the constructor of our superclass.
And then after that I'll know what to do with this keyword.
Let me show you.
If I do console dot log here and do this and I run that gives an error because in order for us to use
that this keyword inside of the constructor when we extend something we have to call super first so
that if I move the console dialog to under the super call and I run look at that I have elf that has
a name and weapon attached to it.
So this because we call the super runs the constructor we now have a instance of character with these
properties and then we can use this dot type to add type to it so that by the very end of our construction
process of ELF we have all our properties set very very cool.
And remember the this keyword simply says who am I.
Who's calling me.
In this case we use the new keyword.
So this is going to be set to elf all right.
But we started this video with us wanting to create an ogre.
So let's do that.
Let's continue on.
Let's create another class that's going to be an ogre class that extends the character.
We do the same thing now.
Let's say that our ogre has a constructor and we want to pass in a few things such as name weapon and
you know what ogres have different colors.
So let's do that.
Let's add a color prop..
And what do we do here.
Well we're gonna call the super class which is character with name and weapon so that now we can use
this keyword to attach new properties to the ogre class.
I'm going to add a color that equals whatever color we give it
and you know what ogres.
They have special powers.
Let's say that ogres can also make forts.
So we have a make Fort because you know they're very powerful obviously and they'll just return.
Let's say strongest fort in the world made nice and easy just like that let's see if this works if I
create let's say Shrek and Shrek is a new ogre with the name of Shrek.
Weapon is going to be a club.
And then finally the color obviously green if I do Shrek docked attack or let's just do Shrek here to
see what we get.
Look at that.
I have a new ogre that was just created for me.
How awesome is that and if I do make forts here and run this look at that I'm able to use make Fort
function or method on Shrek but if I go and do make fort to Dobie no Doby can make for it.
He's very very weak.
There's not much that he can do.
He's just the house elf.
So let's go back to attack your.
How cool was that.
We were able to keep our code nice and organized and extend our base class character to create all these
different characters in our game Elf.
We have ogre we can keep creating different things like night magicians princesses kings queens and
we can reuse code that we've run before but also extend these classes to have their own individual unique
things like properties like type or even methods like make for it.
This is a simple example but you can imagine the power of this as we get more and more properties and
methods and bigger and bigger objects.
Now let's take a break here and revisit this code in the next video.