Welcome back.
Let's talk a little bit more about inheritance.
When we created make fort here that is we created our own method just for the ogre class.
What we actually did underneath the hood was we extended the prototype right.
It's like saying ogre dot prototype dot make for it and you can see over here that's even showing me
that I have make for it underneath the hood javascript created this for us because we used class keyword.
And I think it looks a lot nicer than having to use prototype.
We've done that before and it got a little confusing.
Now the cool part about this beyond the fact that it just looks a lot cleaner things just make sense
and we're using some really important object oriented principles like classes and extending and creating
subclasses and using the new keyword to create instances.
We're also using underneath the hood the prototype of inheritance of javascript to make these inheritance
prototype chains between our objects to test that.
Everything is linked properly.
Let's do a few tests.
Let's say that we want console dialogue to have let's say ogre is prototype of what is ogre a prototype
of well if I do Shrek here and I run faults because again this is a little tricky ogre is a constructor
function we want to check ogre dot prototype which is the object that contains all the properties and
methods we have available.
So if I do this and run I get true awesome.
What if I do something like this.
What if I do character dot prototype.
Is that a prototype of ogre if I run this.
And let's spell that correctly.
Let's try this.
I get false again and we have to remember ogre dot prototype.
If I run I get true all right all this prototype stuff is a little bit confusing.
There's a better way to check these connections using the instance of keyword.
So let's do that.
I can say Dolby is that an instance of health the elf class yep it's an instance of ELF class.
That's great.
Is it an instance of ogre.
No it's not an instance of ogre.
What about character.
Is it an instance of character yet it's an instance of character because well it extends all the way
up from character so remember that distinction instance is when we use the new keyword from a class
we create an instance of a class instance is essentially creating a version of the class inheritance
which is what we do with the keyword extends is inheriting something from a higher class inheritance
in JavaScript doesn't actually copy our functionality.
It doesn't just simply copy whatever we have in character.
Instead it simply links up the prototype chain.
So you're not creating copies and making things inefficient instead whenever it doesn't find something
let's say on the ogre class it's going to look up to the ogres superclass which is character.
So it's creating these efficient linking in JavaScript using prototype all inheritance.
And I want to remind you unlike other class based languages javascript is well just objects it's objects
inheriting from objects.
That's it.
There are no technical classes in languages like Java on the other hand they have classes that well
are actual classes.
There are things and classes inherit from classes.
The interesting thing is that languages like Java and C++ actually copy objects.
When we do something like extend instead of what we do with JavaScript which is that we link and the
objects are referenced there's actually a bit of efficiency there in terms of memory.
All right let's finish off and wrap all of this up into what we've learned about object oriented programming
so far.
I'll see in the next video by.